Stephen E. Malawista papers
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
- Grant and contract proposals, Series V
  - Major NIH grants: NIH R01 AR10493: "Biophysical Mechanisms in Leukocytes and Melanocytes", Subseries 1
    - NIH 5 R01 AR10493, 2004 (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - NIH 5 R01 AR10493-36, 2005 (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - NIH R01 AR10493, Closeout, 2008 (Box 41, Folder 4)
      End of this grant that was renewed over 35 years.
  - Major NIH grants: NIH: R01 AR40452: "Pathogenesis of Lyme Disease: Molecular Probes", Subseries 2
    5-year award in which Malawista served as Principal Investigator and Ruth Montgomery as Co-Investigator.
    - NIH: R01 AR40452, 1989 (Box 41, Folder 5)
    - NIH: R01 AR40452, 1989-1990 (Box 41, Folder 6)
    - NIH: R01 AR40452, 1991-1993 (Box 41, Folder 7)
    - NIH: R01 AR40452, 1994-1996 (Box 41, Folder 8)
  - Major NIH grants: NIH R01 A143558: "Lyme Disease: Host Parasite Interactions Affecting Disease Persistence", 1998; Subseries 3
    Original proposal for a five-year award. Dr. Ruth Montgomery would be working 45% time on it.
    - NIH R01 A143558, 1998 (Box 41, Folder 9)
    - NIH 5 R01 AI43558-02, 1999-2000 (Box 41, Folder 10)
    - NIH 5 R01 AI43558-03, 2000 (Box 41, Folder 11)
    - NIH 5 R01 AI43558-04, 2001 (Box 41, Folder 12)
    - NIH 5 R01 A143558-05, Ruth Montgomery, Acting P.I., 2002-2003 (Box 41, Folder 13)
  - Major NIH grants: NIH R21 AR003457: "Resolution of Gouty Inflammation", 2005-2008; Subseries 4
    The R21 type grant was an "Exploratory/Developmental Research Grant." Malawista was the P.I., Ruth Montgomery also worked on the grant, and Charles Serhan of Harvard was a consultant.
    - NIH R21 AR003457, 2005 (Box 41, Folder 14)
    - NIH R21 AR003457 (revised), 2006 (Box 41, Folder 15)
    - NIH R21 AR053457-01, 2007 (Box 41, Folder 16)
    - NIH R21 AR053457-02, 2008 (Box 41, Folder 17)
  - Major NIH grants: NIH Program Project Grant: 1 P01 AI39548, "Lyme Disease: Pathogenesis and Protection," Stephen W. Barthold, P.I., 1990-1998; Subseries 5
    This was a 5-year Program Project Grant on Lyme disease in which many Yale physicians and scientists collaborated. Stephen Barthold, DVM, PhD, was in the Section of Comparative Medicine at Yale. Malawista was P.I. of the second project of the grant, "Host-Parasite Interactions that Determine the Rate of B. burgdorferi in vivo." The grant was awarded in 1991.
    - NIH Program Project Grant, "Lyme Disease; Pathogenesis and Protection," Fred Kantor, P. I., 1990 January (Box 42, Folder 1)
      Initial application for this large grant with several parts, each with its own principal investigator. Malawista was to be in charge of Project #2, "Probes for B. burgorferi DNA in Ticks, Mice and Men." This version of the proposal was presumably not approved. The 1991 proposal with Stephen Barthold as P.I. did receive funding for five years.
    - NIH 1 P01 AI30548, "Lyme Disease; Pathogenesis and Protection," Stephen Barthold, P.I., 1990 October (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - NIH 1 P01 AI30548-01A1, 1991 (Box 42, Folder 3)
    - NIH 5 P01 AI30548-02, 1992 (Box 42, Folder 4)
    - NIH 5 P01 AI30548-03, 1993 (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - NIH 1 P01 AI30548, 1994 (Box 42, Folder 6)
      This is a much expanded renewal application consisting of "five interactive projects and three supporting cores." The request was for over 7 million dollars.
    - NIH 1 P01 AI30548, 1995 (Box 42, Folder 7)
      Another attempt at renewal.
    - NIH P01 A130548, Request for a bridge grant, 1998 (Box 42, Folder 8)
  - Other NIH and federal grant proposals, Subseries 6
    These are shorter grants or fellowships, or proposals that were not funded.
    - NIH Research Career Development Award, 1968 (Box 43, Folder 1)
      Request of William L. Nusser to Alvan Feinstein at Yale to comment upon the application on behalf of Stephen Malawista for a Research Career Development Award, and Feinstein's extremely positive response.
    - NIH: Rheumatology Training Grant proposal, 1970 (Box 43, Folder 2)
      The purpose of the grant was to provide a comprehensive two-year post-residency training program for four selected post-doctoral trainees.
    - NIH: 1R01 CA 16345-01 "Control of Cellular Differentiation: Tumor Cell Hybrids," not funded, 1973-1974 (Box 43, Folder 3)
    - NIH: Connecticut Regional Medical Program, "Yale Affiliated Arthritis Program," not funded, 1974 (Box 43, Folder 4)
      The NIH-funded Connecticut Regional Medical Center had money "earmarked" for arthritis. Yale's proposal was not funded.
    - NIH Training Grant: "Training Program in Investigative Rheumatology," not funded, 1975 (Box 43, Folder 5)
      This was a 5-year proposal (1975-1980) to train postdoctoral fellows. It was not funded.
    - NIH Program Grant: "Molecular Physiology and Pathology of Lysosomes," S.E. Malawista, P. Greengard, and J. Rosenbaum, not funded, 1975 (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - NIH: CA-17207 "Control of Cellular Differentiation: Tumor Cell Hybrids," not funded, 1975 (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - NIH: "Yale Arthritis Center," Leo M. Cooney, Jr., P.I., not funded, 1976-1977 (Box 43, Folder 8)
      This was a large proposal in response to the National Institute of Arthritis, Metabolism, and Digestive Diseases' plan to establish Multipurpose Arthritis Centers at universities. Folder also includes correspondence of Malawista with members of the Senate and House of Representatives in Connecticut about the proposal. Yale's proposal was not funded.
    - NIH: 2 R01 AM 20358-02S1 GMA, "Lyme Arthritis: A New Epidemic Disease (Supplement)," Allen C. Steere P.I., 1978-1979 (Box 43, Folder 9)
      Malawista was one of a number of investigators on this proposal. The supplementary proposal was rejected. This collection does not contain the original proposal.
    - NIH: Senior International Fellowship, 1986 (Box 43, Folder 10)
      Proposal to work during a sabbatical in Paris under the sponsorship of Dr. Mary C. Weiss. The title of the proposal is "Molecular Genetics of Liver-Specific Gene Expression." Malawista received the award for 1987-1988.
    - NIH: "Protective Epitopes Important in Lyme Borreliosis," Fred S. Kantor, P.I., 1989 (Box 43, Folder 11)
      This grant was not funded but it probably served as a precursor to the Program Project Grant, "Lyme Disease: Pathogenesis and Protection."
    - NIH Training Grant: "Training Program in Investigative Rheumatology," not funded, 1989 (Box 44, Folder 1)
    - NIH: "Multi-Locus Molecular Detection of Borrelia burgdorferi," David H. Persing, P.I., 1991 (Box 44, Folder 2)
      Malawista was one of several co-investigators on this proposal by David H. Persing, M.D., Ph.D. of the Mayo Foundation.
    - NIH: "Molecular Diagnosis and Monitoring of Lyme Disease," David H. Persing, P.I., 1991 (Box 44, Folder 3)
      Malawista was one of several Co-investigators in this proposal.
    - NIH: "Serologic Diagnosis of Lyme Disease Using Recombinant Borrelia burgdorferi Antigens," P.I. Daniel Rahn, 1991 (Box 44, Folder 4)
      In this proposal, Malawista would be an unpaid consultant.
    - NIH Fogarty Senior International Fellowship: "Motile Function of Human Neutrophils and Cytoplasts", 1993-1996 (Box 44, Folder 5)
      Malawista received this award for his sabbatical in Paris in 1994-1995.
    - NIH: "Interactions of Phagocytes with B. burgdorferi in Mice", 1994 (Box 44, Folder 6)
      R01 five-year proposal in which Malawista, the P.I., would spend 20% of his time and Ruth Montgomery would spend 90% of her time. Other investigators were Stephen W. Barthold, and Keith A. Joyner, all at Yale University School of Medicine.
    - CDC: "Effect of Tick Saliva on Phagocyte Motility and Function," Ruth Montgomery, P.I., 1997 (Box 44, Folder 7)
      Malawista was to be an investigator on this grant and would be paid 5% of his salary from it. The application appears to be in response to the Center for Disease Control announcement number 800. The folder also contains a proposal to the Arthritis Foundation for a grant with the same title.
    - NIH Training Grant: "Training in Investigative Rheumatology, Joseph Craft, P.I., 2000 (Box 44, Folder 8)
      The NIH-sponsored training program in investigative rheumatology was begun in 1976. It trained both M.D.s and Ph.D.s in an area "that focuses upon the mechanisms of rheumatologic and immunologic diseases." Malawista was one of 21 collaborators.
    - NIH AR04-06 "Endogenous and Therapeutic Control of Gouty Inflammation", 2004 (Box 44, Folder 9)
      Folder includes a companion grant under the same title by Paul Naccache, University of Laval, France.
    - NIH: R21 "Lipid-derived Regulators of Chemotaxis in Human Plasma", 2005 (Box 44, Folder 10)
      Malawista would be P.I., Ruth Montgomery, investigator, and Charles Serhan, Harvard University, consultant.
    - NIH: Resubmission of R21 "Lipid-derived Regulators of Chemotaxis in Human Plasma", 2006 (Box 44, Folder 11)
    - NIH: Resubmission of R21 "Lipid-derived Regulators of Chemotaxis in Human Plasma", 2007 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - NIH: N01-AI-50031, "Toll-Like Receptor Responsiveness in the Elderly and Immunosuppressed, Erol Fikrig, P.I., 2005 (Box 45, Folder 2)
      This was to be a large multi-investigator project involving Malawista and Ruth Montgomery, among others. The proposal was "in response to the announcement of a contract to address immune function and biodefense in immunocompromised patients groups." This proposal was called by Malawista the "Biodefense Contract." It would especially concern West Nile Virus.
      The folder contains materials on planning for the application, including IRB approval, but not the proposal itself.
    - NIH: Pilot Feasibility Study as part of the Yale Skin Disease Research Core Center, 2005-2006 (Box 45, Folder 3)
      The Yale Disease Research Core Center, sponsored by NIH, was under Dr. Robert E. Tigelaar, Professor of Dermatology and Immunobiology at Yale. Malawista's proposal, "Modulation of the Inflammatory Response in Human Plasma," was sent to NIH in both 2005 and 2006 and was a small grant for $25,000 in direct costs to work with Tigelaar. It may not have been funded.
    - NIH Pioneer Award: "A New Therapeutic Blood Component: Cryopreservable Neutrophil Surrogates", 2007 (Box 45, Folder 4)
    - NIH Pioneer Award: "A New Therapeutic Blood Component: Cryopreservable Neutrophil Surrogates", 2008 (Box 45, Folder 5)
      Presumably another attempt to get this award.
    - NIH: "Acute Inflammation by Human Neutrophils in Human Skin Xenografts", 2007 (Box 45, Folder 6)
      This is another effort to work on the functions of neutrophils in the skin, taking advantage of the Yale Skin Disease Research Core.
    - NIH: "Ambivalent Association of Human Neutrophils with Urate Crystals", 2008 (Box 45, Folder 7)
    - NIH: "Ambivalent Association of Human Neutrophils with Urate Crystals", 2009 (Box 45, Folder 8)
  - Arthritis Foundation, Subseries 7
    Next to NIH, the Arthritis Foundation was a major source of funding for Malawista and for students that Malawista was mentoring.
    - Arthritis Foundation: Arthritis Clinical Research Center, 1969 (Box 45, Folder 9)
      The original proposal asked for $69,593 for two years, 1969 to 1971. Among those supported in part by this proposal were Drs. Robert Gifford and James D. Kenney. The Arthritis Foundation approved $12,000 for one year. Malawista noted that he had previously received grants from the Arthritis Foundation and its Connecticut Chapter.
    - Arthritis Foundation: "Lyme Disease: Molecular Probes for Pathogenesis and Diagnosis", 1989-1992 (Box 45, Folder 10)
      This proposal was funded for three years beginning in 1990.
    - Arthritis Foundation: "Cellular interactions of the agent for Lyme disease, Borrelia burgdorferi," Ruth Montgomery, P.I. (Box 45, Folder 11)
      Two successive proposals under the same title in 1990 and 1991. Malawista was to act as supervisor on the proposal. See following folder for more on the proposals.
    - Arthritis Foundation: Correspondence of Malawista on grants, 1990-1991 (Box 45, Folder 12)
      Malawista discusses both his own proposals and grants from the Arthritis Foundation and the proposals of Ruth Montgomery (previous folder).
    - Arthritis Foundation; "Mechanisms that allow Borrelia burgdorferi to evade host defenses: diagnostic implications'", 1993-1996 (Box 45, Folder 13)
    - Arthritis Foundation: "Antigenic Substitution in Borrelia burgdorferi and Bacterial Persistence in the Mammalian Host,", 1996-1999 (Box 45, Folder 14)
  - G. Harold and Leila Y. Mathers Charitable Foundation, Subseries 8
    The G. Harold and Leila Y. Mathers Foundation was another major source of support for Malawista's work on Lyme disease. Malawista corresponded with Mr. James H. Handelman, Executive Director, Mount Kisco, New York.
    - Mathers Foundation: Richard Flavell/Stephen Malawista, Lyme diseases research, 1991 (Box 46, Folder 1)
      Flavell and Malawista received a sizeable three-year award in 1991.
    - Mathers Foundation: Richard Flavell/Stephen Malawista, Lyme disease research, 1992-1993 (Box 46, Folder 2)
    - Mathers Foundation: The Lyme Disease Research Program at Yale University School of Medicine, 1994-1995 (Box 46, Folder 3)
    - Mathers Foundation: The Lyme Disease Research Program at Yale University School of Medicine, 1996-1999 (Box 46, Folder 4)
    - Mathers Foundation, Unrestricted gift to the Section of Rheumatology, 1999-2000 (Box 46, Folder 5)
      See previous folder.
    - Mathers Foundation, Bridge grant, 2003, 2005 (Box 46, Folder 6)
      Malawista was in a position of needing funds to keep his laboratory and its personnel going until new grants came in. The Mathers Foundation agreed to help.
  - New Haven Foundation/ Community Foundation for Greater New Haven, Subseries 9
    - New Haven Foundation, Equipment for Arthritis Research, 1988-1991 (Box 46, Folder 7)
      This application was funded.
    - Community Foundation for Greater New Haven, Lyme Disease bridge funding, 1998 (Box 46, Folder 8)
      Proposal to continue Malawista's and Ruth Montgomery's research on Lyme disease through a gap in NIH funding. Malawista received a two-year award.
    - Community Foundation for Greater New Haven, Lyme Disease bridge funding, 2002-2004 (Box 46, Folder 9)
      Proposal for bridge funding for Malawista's and Montgomery's research on Lyme disease until new money came in from NIH. The first version of the proposal was turned down as being too expensive. It is not clear what happened to Malawista's revised proposal.
  - Other granting agencies, Subseries 10
    - Connecticut Lupus Foundation, "Inflammatory Disease Teaching Materials," not funded, 1975 (Box 46, Folder 10)
    - The Donoghue Foundation: "Lyme Arthritis: Control of Inflammation", 2004-2007 (Box 46, Folder 11)
      Folder contains proposals from 2004 and 2005
    - Estate of Reeve E. Donoghue, 1998 (Box 46, Folder 12)
      $10,000 gift from the estate of Reeve E. Donoghue for scleroderma research in the Section of Rheumatology.
    - Doris Duke Charitable Foundation, New York, 1997 (Box 46, Folder 13)
      Separated Materials
      A feeler letter from Malawista to the Foundation regarding possible support of Lyme disease research.
    - The Ellison Medical Foundation, Bethesda, Md., 2003 (Box 46, Folder 14)
      Rejection of Malawista's proposal on "Colchicine and theophylline in asthma" and summary of reviewers' comments.
    - Eshe Fund, New York, 2004-2005 (Box 46, Folder 15)
      The Eshe Fund donated money for 2004 and 2005 in support of Lyme disease research under Malawista.
    - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, Fellowship, 2000 (Box 46, Folder 16)
      Draft application for the 2001 Guggenheim Fellowship Competition.
    - John A. Hartford Foundation, New York, "A Laboratory and Clinical Study of Rheumatoid Arthritis", 1969 (Box 46, Folder 17)
      This was an early grant covering part of the salaries of Dr. James D. Kenney and Dr. Robert H. Gifford.
    - Richard or Helen Haskell Fund, 1970-1981 (Box 46, Folder 18)
      This was a gift of $100,000 for the study of arthritis. Some of the money was used by Malawista.
    - Inflammatory Diseases Foundation, New Haven, 1969-1970 (Box 46, Folder 19)
      The Inflammatory Disease Foundation was founded in 1969 by Malawista and others as a non-profit in New Haven to raise funds for research on inflammatory diseases. The folder contains a plan for a brochure titled "Target: Inflammatory Diseases" and the completed brochure.
    - The National Foundation - March of Dimes, 1969 (Box 46, Folder 20)
      Proposal by Malawista to the Birth Defects Research Program of the National Foundation, titled "The intracellular defect(s) of polymorphonuclear leucocytes from patients with chronic granulomatous disease of childhood."
    - Swebelius Trust, Cancer Research Awards: "Control of Cellular Differentiation: Tumor Cell Hybrids", 1975 (Box 46, Folder 21)
      The proposal was not funded.
    - Yale University School of Medicine BRSG Fluid Research Funds: Paul B. Hoffer/ Malawista, "Localization of Human Leukocyte Fragments in an In Vivo Rabbit Abscess Model", 1987 (Box 46, Folder 22)
      The Medical School offered small grants for initial funding of new faculty, pilot studies, and limited interim funding. This proposal by Paul Hoffer and Malawista was titled "Localization of Human Leucocyte Fragments in an In Vivo Rabbit Abscess Model." It was not funded.
  - Contracts with drug and other companies, Subseries 11
    - Hematek Partners, Scheer & Company, Branford, Conn., "Chemotactic, phagocytic, and microbial function of stored human polymorphonuclear leukocytes", 1989 (Box 47, Folder 1)
      This is a "Business Plan" by Hematek to "develop a novel, proprietary technology that makes possible the extended storage of granulocytes." Included in the folder is Malawista's description of the six-month project.
    - Pfizer, Groton, Conn., P.I. Paul Hoffer, 1986-1987 (Box 47, Folder 2)
      Paul Hoffer, professor of diagnostic radiology at Yale, proposed to investigate of "A radionuclide method to monitor the progress of rheumatoid arthritis." The primary object was to validate the use of Ga-67 to "assess the efficacy of drug treatment." Malawista was an advisor on this project.
    - G.D. Searle & Co., Chicago: "Effect of Colchicine on Rheumatoid Arthritis Disease Activity in Patients Concurrently Taking Misoprostol and NSAIDS", 1989-1990 (Box 47, Folder 3)
      Although called a grant, this funding provided to Malawista was more like a contract from the drug company G.D. Searle to do a clinical test of its drug Cytotec (misoprostol). Misoprostal was similar to the natural prostaglandins, and could serve as a replacement for patients taking aspirin and similar drugs (NSAIDs) that could cause ulcers.
    - G.D. Searle: published materials on Cytotec (misoprostol), ca. 1990 (Box 47, Folder 4)
    - G.D. Searle & Co., 1991 (Box 47, Folder 5)
    - G.D. Searle & Co., 1992-1994 (Box 47, Folder 6)
    - Therakos, West Chester, Pa.: "Extracorporeal Treatment of Rheumatoid Arthritis" (Restricted), 1987-1990 (Box 47, Folder 7)
      The project was to test the therapeutic effect of photopheresis on rheumatoid arthritis. Folder includes correspondence, a protocol (4978), and patient names. Restricted.
    - Therakos: Malawista, letter to U.S. Rep. John D. Dingell, 1992 January 24 (Box 47, Folder 8)
      Letter of complaint for how his project was treated at the meeting of the FDA Rheumatoid Arthritis Advisory Panel. Dingell was Chairman of the House Subcommittee on Oversight and Investigations.
- Lyme disease files, Part 1 (open), Series VI
  Arrangement
  Malawista maintained a category for material on Lyme disease, but the materials were disorganized. Materials on Lyme disease were scattered throughout his papers. This series contains papers that do not have individual patient information and therefore are open for research. The clippings, popular articles, and research articles were all collected by Malawista. The arrangement of this series is that of the archivist. Malawista's papers on Lyme disease can be found under Series 4, Submission of manuscripts for publication, and Series 10, Published articles(reprints). His presentations on Lyme disease and Yale symposia on Lyme disease are under Series 9, Talks and Travel.
  - Yale University news releases, drafts, and related, 1976-1983; Subseries 1
    - Yale University news releases and drafts, 1976-1983 (Box 48, Folder 1)
      An earlier Yale press release is found in the folder for Allen C. Steere and Malawista's first paper on Lyme disease. See Box 23, folder 3.
    - Yale University news releases and other publicity, 1986-1993 (Box 48, Folder 2)
    - Draft of an article for Yale Alumni Magazine, 1983 May 25 (Box 48, Folder 3)
      The article was to appear in the June 1983 issue.
    - Yale Medicine articles on Lyme Disease (Box 48, Folder 4)
      Issue of Yale Medicine, Spring 1996, containing Marc Wortman, "The Lyme Disease Dream Team," 1-15; Malawista's revisions on a draft of this article; issue of Yale Medicine, Fall 1998, containing "Lyme Disease Vaccines Prove Effective," 4.
    - Yale-New Haven Hospital article in Yale-New Haven, Summer 1990 (Box 48, Folder 5)
      The main article on Lyme disease in this issue is Bruce Reynolds, "The tick that mad New Haven famous," pp. 7-10.
    - SmithKline Beecham agreement with Yale to develop a vaccine for Lyme disease, 1992 July 22 (Box 48, Folder 6)
      This folder contains a formal announcement by SmithKline Beecham and photocopies of newspaper articles resulting from the announcement. These are Malawista's copies of the announcement and articles given to him by the Yale University School of Medicine, Office of Public Information.
  - Popular articles on Lyme disease written or corrected by Malawista, Subseries 2
    These are short popular or semi-popular articles by Malawista that are not in his CV or, more often, drafts of articles that reporters or editors sent to Malawista to correct.
    - "Lyme Arthritis" for Rheumatology News, 1977 (Box 48, Folder 7)
    - Questions for an article in the Gazette, "serving the Lower Connecticut River Valley", 1978 (Box 48, Folder 8)
      David Holahan, the managing editor, sent the questions to Marje Noyes, in the Office of Public Information at Yale School of Medicine. She sent a draft of a press release for Malawista, Allen C. Steere, and John A. Hardin to review.
    - Pre-publication article for Rheumatology News, 1978 (Box 48, Folder 9)
    - News release for International Medical News Service, 1979 (Box 48, Folder 10)
    - Jonathan A. Leonard, "Lyme Disease" for Discover, edited by A.C. Steere and S.E. Malawista, 1980 (Box 48, Folder 11)
    - Draft of JAMA article on Lyme disease, 1982 July 12 (Box 48, Folder 12)
      Unedited draft sent by Phil Gundy, Senior Associate editor of JAMA, for review by Malawista and Steere.
    - Malawista's contribution to pamphlet, "Lyme Disease" for the Connecticut Chapter of the Arthritis Foundation, 1982-1983, 1986 (Box 48, Folder 13)
      Correspondence, drafts, and copies of the foldout brochure on Lyme disease and its later revision. The brochure was titled Lyme Disease (originally called Lyme arthritis): facts you should know about a new disease that has affected hundreds of people in Connecticut ." It was "prepared by the Yale School of Medicine for the Connecticut Chapter Arthritis Foundation."
    - Draft article on the treatment of Lyme disease for Internal Medicine Digest, 1984 April 27 (Box 48, Folder 14)
      Sent by the copy editor to Malawista for accuracy and illustrations.
    - Draft of "Fundamental aspects of Rheumatology," for Current Rheumatology, 1984 (Box 48, Folder 15)